<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.16 -->
<document source="/Users/kmoy001/libcellml/libcellml-src/docs/current_thinking.rst">
    <target refid="libcellmlcurrentthinking"></target>
    <section ids="current-thinking-for-libcellml libcellmlcurrentthinking" names="current\ thinking\ for\ libcellml libcellmlcurrentthinking">
        <title>Current Thinking for libCellML</title>
        <paragraph>This document simply outlines some of the current rationale that has an influence on how the codebase is developed.</paragraph>
        <bullet_list bullet="-">
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Temporarily dealing with external documents that are stored on the local file system (relative to the current CellML model document).</paragraph>
                <bullet_list bullet="-">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Allows testing of the most common model import scenario (local files addressed with a relative URL).</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Absolves libcellml from fetching files and communicating across the Internet.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Expect to provide another layer that would perform this role as a libCellML I/O library, which would allow the removal of this temporary inclusion.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>No avenue to retrieve remote external references.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </bullet_list>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Serialise and deserialise from a string.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Present a useful interface not one tied to the <reference internal="False" refuri="https://www.w3.org/XML/">XML</reference> serialisation structure.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Validation is quite separate (you are free to make invalid <reference internal="False" refuri="https://www.cellml.org/">CellML</reference> models).</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Public API treats MathML as strings only.</paragraph>
                <bullet_list bullet="-">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Internal to the code generation we are currently creating our own <reference internal="False" refuri="https://www.w3.org/Math/">MathML</reference> object model based on an abstract syntax tree.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Minimal implementation to support the immediate requirement of code generation.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Expect to provide another layer that would handle MathML as a separate thing, potentially linking back to the advanced functionality envisions for symbolic analysis of the model.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Internal to the validator, the MathML strings are parsed into a DOM for use in schema validation against the MathML schema.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </bullet_list>
            </list_item>
        </bullet_list>
    </section>
</document>
